ACWA's Sidney Hillman Scrapbooks 5619/003
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ACWA's Sidney Hillman Scrapbooks
1910-1964
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America
5619/003
21.67 cubic feet
18 linear feet
Photograph albums, Scrapbooks, News clippings.
This collection consists of photograph albums and scrapbooks documenting strikes, organizing campaigns, and biographies of Sidney Hillman and Jacob Potofsky.
6849655
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff
Date completed:
March 08, 2010
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, July, 2010
Biographical / Historical
The Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, the most significant union representing workers in the men's clothing industry, was founded in New York City in 1914 as a breakaway movement from the United Garment Workers. Radical and immigrant workers in the tailors' and cutters' locals were the core of the seceding group, which advocated industrial unionism and economic strikes in opposition to the UGW's craft organization, which they saw as conservative and timid. Their diverging views had come to the fore during the historic 1910 dispute at the Chicago firm Hart, Schaffner, and Marx. The opposition called the strike against the UGW leadership's advice, and reached a path-breaking agreement with management that established an arbitration system to settle disputes.
Members flocked to the new union. Around 50,000 strong at its founding, by 1920 the ACWA counted about 170,000 members. Initially composed mostly of immigrants of Jewish European descent with Socialist leanings, the ACWA quickly welcomed members of a great number of nationalities and diverse backgrounds. Like in other garment unions, most workers and many members were women, but the leadership was predominantly male, a situation that did not change for many decades. Early on the union adopted a centralized administrative structure combined with industrial unionism, with the joint boards' by-laws having precedence over those of locals.
Espousing a philosophy perhaps brought over by its early immigrant socialist members, the Amalgamated went beyond bread and butter issues and adopted a distinctive form of social unionism that was largely absent in the American labor movement. Starting in the 1920s, it provided educational opportunities and recreational facilities for its members, as well as services such as an insurance plan, banks offering personal loans at low interest rates, low-cost housing cooperatives, medical clinics, and even union-owned restaurants.
Sidney Hillman was the first president of the new union and the most important officer in its history. He applied his experience as bargaining representative in Chicago to the whole industry. Under his leadership the union made significant strides in securing better wages and working conditions for its members, and at the same time it consolidated gains and provided stability to the industry through the widespread adoption of the arbitration system tested at Hart, Schaffner, and Marx. Hillman paid close attention to industry issues, such as production, pricing, and marketing. In order to help management meet the competition of non-union firms, the union conducted studies of efficiency, work methods, and factory costs. Letters to the official publication of the union, Advance, document the controversy that ensued within the union over what was perceived to be collaboration with management.
Hillman also understood the importance of labor's involvement in national affairs and political action. In the 1920s the ACWA sent delegates to the Conference for Progressive Political Action and to the Farmer-labor party conventions. Although many members and officers were Socialists, the union stopped short of officially endorsing the party. Communist attempts at gaining influence within the union were firmly curbed. Hillman's participation in national affairs and politics became prominent during the New Deal, when he became a close advisor to Franklin D. Roosevelt on labor and economic issues. He also served on the board of the National Recovery Administration. Later, during World War II, he helped establish the Labor's Non Partisan League. He was also named associate director of the Office of Production Management, which assisted in mobilizing the nation's resources for the war effort. Hillman's prestige perhaps reflected the healthy condition of his union, which by the end of the conflict was strong and stable.
During the post World War II period the union faced a number of significant challenges. Membership continued to grow (peaking at 395,000 in 1968), but the union's political influence and visibility in national affairs declined. In their never ending pursuit of lower production costs, many firms relocated to the South, forcing the union to engage in large organizing efforts. Simultaneously, signs began to appear of changes that would lead to the almost complete demise of the domestic apparel industry and, ultimately, to the erosion of union membership. Foreign imports of cheap clothing goods steadily grew in the 1950s and 1960s, and mushroomed in the following two decades, plunging employment in the apparel sector into a steady decline. Union efforts to stem the tide included Buy American campaigns and extensive lobbying in Congress, but they were to no avail. In 1976, the ACWA merged with the Textile Workers of America to become the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union. Despite successful and much publicized nationwide actions such as the Farah boycott and the J.P. Stevens corporate campaign, the woes threatening the union's existence continued unabated. The fate of the domestic industry was sealed in the late 1970s and the 1980s by the flight of firms chasing tax breaks and cheap labor abroad. By 1995, when ACTWU voted to merge with the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, their combined membership was 350,000. The new Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE!) seemed poised to infuse new life in a troubled union.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related collections: 5619: Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America 5619/005: ACWA's Bessie Hillman Papers 5619/010: ACWA's Jacob Potofsky Records from the President's Office And all other 5619 collections.
Textile workers--Labor unions--New York (State); Clothing workers--Labor unions--New York (State); Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America; Hillman, Sidney, 1887-1946; Potofsky, Jacob, 1892-1979; Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union --Archives; Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees; UNITE HERE (Organization) --Archives
6849655
- Federation of Jewish Charities, 1941 (Box 22)
  Scope and Contents
  Photo Album, Vol. 1.
- Dinner for David Drechsler, 1947 (Box 23)
  Photo Album, Vol. 2.
- Jacob S. Potofsky, 1947-1948 (Box 24)
  Photo Album, Vol. 3.
- Jacob S. Potofsky, 1949 (Box 25)
  Photo Album, Vol. 4.
- Jacob S. Potofsky, 1950 (Box 26)
  Photo Album, Vol. 5.
- Jacob S. Potofsky, 1950-1951 (Box 27)
  Photo Album, Vol. 6.
- Jacob S. Potofsky, 1951-9153 (Box 28)
  Photo Album, Vol. 7.
- Jacob S. Potofsky, 1954-1958 (Box 29)
  Photo Album, Vol. 8.
- Jacob S. Potofsky, 1957-1959 (Box 30)
  Photo Album, Vol. 9.
- Latin American Committee, CIO, 1946-1954 (Box 31)
  Photo Album, Vol. 10.
- Silver Jubilee, 1940 (Box 32)
  Photo Album, Vol. 11.
- 15th Biennial Convention, ACWA, 1946 (Box 33)
  Photo Album, Vol. 12. May 6-10, 1946. Atlantic City, NJ
- 16th Biennial Convention, ACWA, 1948 (Box 34)
  Photo Album, Vol. 13. May 10-15, 1948. Atlantic City, NJ
- 17th Biennial Convention, ACWA, 1950 (Box 35)
  Photo Album, Vol. 14. May 15, 1950. Cleveland, OH
- 18th Biennial Convention, ACWA, 1952 (Box 36)
  Photo Album, Vol. 15. May 12-16, 1952. Atlantic City, NJ
- 19th Biennial Convention, 40th Anniversary, ACWA, 1954 (Box 37)
  Photo Album, Vol. 16. May 10-14, 1954. Atlantic City, NJ
- 20th Biennial Convention, ACWA, 1956 (Box 38)
  Photo Album, Vol. 17. May 21-25, 1956,. Washington, DC
- 21st Biennial Convention, ACWA, 1958 (Box 39)
  Photo Album, Vol. 18. May 12-16, 1958. Atlantic City, NJ
- 22nd Biennial Convention, ACWA, 1960 (Box 40)
  Photo Album, Vol. 19. May 30-June 3, 1960. Bal Harbour, FL
- 23rd Biennial Convention, ACWA, 1962 (Box 41)
  Photo Album, Vol. 20. May 14-16, 1962. Atlantic City, NJ
- 30th Anniversary, Pennsylvania Joint Board. Honoring David Monas, August 24, 1963. (Box 42)
  Photo Album, Vol. 21.
- Chicago strike, 1915 (Box 43)
  Scrapbook, Vol. 22.
- ACWA clippings, 1920-1921 (Box 44)
  Scrapbook, Vol. 23.
- ACWA clippings, 1921 (Box 45)
  Scrapbook, Vol. 24.
- St. Louis strike, 1933 (Box 46)
  Scrapbook, Vol. 31.
- Leo Wolman, 1914-1933 (Box 47)
  Scrapbook, no number
- Baltimore strike, 1932 (Box 48)
  Scrapbook, Vol. 29.
- Baltimore strike, 1932 (Box 49)
  Scrapbook, Vol. 30.
- Jacob S. Potofsky, 1940-1945 (Box 50)
  Scrapbook, Vol. 35.
- American Labor Party, ALP, 1936-1944 (Box 51)
  Scrapbook, Vol. 38.
- Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, 1936-1938 (Box 52)
  Scrapbook, Vol. 33. English and Yiddish
- Partners in Progress. Report of the International Advisory Board, March 1951 (Box 53)
  Scrapbook, Vol. 49. A Sampling of Press and Radio Reaction
- Press Book 1: General Magazines and Labor Press, 1964 (Box 54)
  Scrapbook, Vol. 50.
- Press Book 2: Newspapers, 1964 (Box 55)
  Scrapbook, Vol. 51.
- Sidney Hillman: With Love and Devotion, 1910-1921 (Box 56)
  Red Book. Vol. 1. English and Yiddish
- Sidney Hillman: The Statesman of the New Industrial Order, 1921-1924 (Box 57)
  Red Book. Vol. 2. English and Yiddish
- Sidney Hillman: The Statesman of the New Industrial Order, 1924-1928 (Box 58)
  Red Book. Vol. 3. English and Yiddish
- Sidney Hillman: The Statesman of the New Industrial Order, 1929-1932 (Box 59)
  Red Book. Vol. 4. English and Yiddish
- Sidney Hillman: The Statesman of the New Industrial Order, 1933-1935 (Box 60)
  Red Book. Vol. 5.
- Sidney Hillman: The Statesman of the New Industrial Order, 1936-1937 (Box 61)
  Red Book. Vol. 6.
- Sidney Hillman: The Statesman of the New Industrial Order, 1938-1939 (Box 62)
  Red Book. Vol. 7.
- Sidney Hillman: The Statesman of the New Industrial Order, 1940-1941 (Box 63)
  Red Book. Vol. 8.
- Sidney Hillman: The Statesman of the New Industrial Order, 1942-1943 (Box 64)
  Red Book. Vol. 9.
- Sidney Hillman: The Statesman of the New Industrial Order, 1944 (Box 65)
  Red Book. Vol. 10: Part 1.
- Sidney Hillman: The Statesman of the New Industrial Order, 1944 (Box 66)
  Red Book. Vol. 10: Part 2.
- Sidney Hillman: The Statesman of the New Industrial Order, 1945-1946 (Box 67)
  Red Book. Vol. 11.
- In Memory of Sidney Hillman: The Statesman of the New Industrial Order, 1946 (Box 68)
  Red Book. Vol. 12.
- Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America: The Record from the Press, 1946-1950 (Box 69)
  Red Book. Vol. 13.
- Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America: The Record from the Press, 1951-1952 (Box 70)
  Red Book. Vol. 14.
- Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America: The Record from the Press, 1953-1954 (Box 71)
  Red Book. Vol. 15.
- Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America: The Record from the Press, 1955-1956 (Box 72)
  Red Book. Vol. 16.
- Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America: The Record from the Press, 1957-1958 (Box 73)
  Red Book. Vol. 17.
- Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, 1959-1961 (Box 74)
  AMSL. Scrapbook.
- ACWA clippings, 1934-1936 (Box 75)
  Scrapbook. Vol. 32.